<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: 6. Impact of secondary trauma	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.researchunbound.org.uk/trauma/6-impact-of-secondary-trauma/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.researchunbound.org.uk/trauma</link>
	<description>Supporting parents and children towards healthy and secure attachments</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 14:59:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
			<item>
				<title>
				By: E Sturdy				</title>
				<link>https://www.researchunbound.org.uk/trauma/6-impact-of-secondary-trauma/#comment-1272</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[E Sturdy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 08:51:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.researchunbound.org.uk/trauma/?page_id=38#comment-1272</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Thank you - excellent article and I am experiencing all aspects of this so it was validating and reassuring to read that it can happen. 
The process of being approved for adoption did not include sufficient realism about these issues. The post-adoption support is also highly patchy and aims more at the child, rightly, while overlooking the parent who is potentially becoming unwell. We need to validate and approve more of the struggle and special extra demands that adoption brings, and the service to society that all adopters are providing.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you &#8211; excellent article and I am experiencing all aspects of this so it was validating and reassuring to read that it can happen.<br />
The process of being approved for adoption did not include sufficient realism about these issues. The post-adoption support is also highly patchy and aims more at the child, rightly, while overlooking the parent who is potentially becoming unwell. We need to validate and approve more of the struggle and special extra demands that adoption brings, and the service to society that all adopters are providing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Helen Robinson				</title>
				<link>https://www.researchunbound.org.uk/trauma/6-impact-of-secondary-trauma/#comment-1252</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Helen Robinson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 20:10:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.researchunbound.org.uk/trauma/?page_id=38#comment-1252</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[We have three adopted children. Two were severely neglected and abused as very young children and one was placed with us at birth due to birth parents domestic violence and alcohol/drug abuse. All three have serious behavioural problems, lots of sensory issues and they struggle with attachment and control. The youngest has learning disabilities. Most people have no idea how difficult life is for us as at school or elsewhere the kids seem (on the face of it) fine. In fact they can be very cute and charming. At home they are at worst violent, self destructive and dangerous - one of my sons has an obsession with knives and fires and lit a fire in his bedroom. He has urinated and defecated on nearly everything in my house and anything he hasnt has been destroyed in some other way. At best these kids totally drain you with constant chatter, nonsense questions or defiance, moodiness or attention grabbing behaviour. Parenting them is utterly exhausting! We have had three years of therapy from Camus which my son was in total control of. I have been left feeling so belittled and foolish in front of therapists and teachers and I don&#039;t have the energy to explain once again why my son cannot take part in an after school activity or have a play date or hand in his homework on time. Its enough for me just to get through one more day! If you&#039;re a professional reading this, please don&#039;t judge parents. Don&#039;t think you know our children better than we do because I can guarantee, what you see with our kids is what they want you to see. How they are for their parents is a totally diffent story and one I wouldn&#039;t wish on my worst enemy.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have three adopted children. Two were severely neglected and abused as very young children and one was placed with us at birth due to birth parents domestic violence and alcohol/drug abuse. All three have serious behavioural problems, lots of sensory issues and they struggle with attachment and control. The youngest has learning disabilities. Most people have no idea how difficult life is for us as at school or elsewhere the kids seem (on the face of it) fine. In fact they can be very cute and charming. At home they are at worst violent, self destructive and dangerous &#8211; one of my sons has an obsession with knives and fires and lit a fire in his bedroom. He has urinated and defecated on nearly everything in my house and anything he hasnt has been destroyed in some other way. At best these kids totally drain you with constant chatter, nonsense questions or defiance, moodiness or attention grabbing behaviour. Parenting them is utterly exhausting! We have had three years of therapy from Camus which my son was in total control of. I have been left feeling so belittled and foolish in front of therapists and teachers and I don&#8217;t have the energy to explain once again why my son cannot take part in an after school activity or have a play date or hand in his homework on time. Its enough for me just to get through one more day! If you&#8217;re a professional reading this, please don&#8217;t judge parents. Don&#8217;t think you know our children better than we do because I can guarantee, what you see with our kids is what they want you to see. How they are for their parents is a totally diffent story and one I wouldn&#8217;t wish on my worst enemy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
			</channel>
</rss>
